About 150 kilometers south of Key West, Florida and 200 kilometers east of Cancun,
在佛羅裡達州基韋斯特以南約 150 公里， 坎昆以東約 200 公里處，
a massive landmass splits the Caribbean Sea from the Gulf of Mexico,
一塊巨大的陸地將 加勒比海與墨西哥灣隔開，
and marks the starting point of the 3.500 kilometer long island chain of the Antilles.
並標誌著長達 3500 公里的安的列斯群島的起點。
The largest island of this archipelago, and 17th largest Island across the whole planet
這個群島中最大的島嶼，也是 全球第 17 大島嶼，
is called Cuba, and while its eccentric leaders have had their fair share of
叫做古巴。雖然
screen time in the past half millenia, the island itself, with its white sandy beaches,
在過去的五百年裡，古巴那些古怪的領導人頻頻出現在公眾視野中，但古巴 島本身，擁有白色沙灘、
towering mogotes, tropical rainforests and cactus savannahs seldom receives the spotlight.
高聳的莫戈特山、熱帶雨林和 仙人掌草原，卻很少受到關注。
Therefore, in this video we will take a closer look at the many mountain ranges scattered around
因此，在本影片中，我們將仔細 觀察散佈在島嶼周圍的眾多山脈
the islands, the 6 ecoregions which make up the rolling hills and fertile plains in between them,
，構成 其間起伏的丘陵和肥沃平原的 6 個生態區，
and the mosaic of kays, mangroves and coral reefs which surround the main island.
以及環繞主島的海溝、紅樹林和珊瑚礁組成的馬賽克景觀 。
Chapter 1: The Mountains At first glance, the island
第一章：山脈 乍一看，
of Cuba appears like a flat stretch, drawn between the two seas, but the monotonous plains
古巴島就像一片平坦的地帶，被拉到 兩海之間，但
of central Cuba are only half the truth. With an age of over 250 million years,
古巴中部單調的平原只是真相的一半。這座島嶼已有 超過 2.5 億年的歷史，
the island is clearly not shaped by recent tectonic activity, but several mountain ranges
顯然不是由近期的 地質構造活動形成的，但幾座山脈
have stood the test of time, and remind us to this date, what immense forces have shaped this island.
經受住了時間的考驗，至今仍在提醒我們 ，是怎樣巨大的力量塑造了這座島嶼。
A total of 4 isolated mountain ranges are standing above the largely flat and
總共有 4 個孤立的山脈 聳立在平坦
fertile plains, turning Cubas homogenic biota into a diverse tropical landscape,
肥沃的平原之上，將古巴單一的 生物群落轉變為多樣化的熱帶景觀，從而
which fosters endemism across many species of flora and fauna.
促進了 許多動植物物種的特有性。
The largest of these mountainous areas are the Nipe-Sagua-Baracoa Mountains,
這些山區中最大的 是尼佩-薩瓜-巴拉科阿山脈，它
which cover the eastern tip of the island, just north of the infamous Guantanamo Bay.
覆蓋了島嶼的東端， 就在臭名昭著的關塔那摩灣以北。
The 3 ranges which are smoothly transitioning between each other,
這三座山脈 彼此平滑過渡，它們
are receiving much of the moist air coming from the Atlantic Ocean, whose clouds are emptying
接收了大量來自大西洋的潮濕空氣 ，大西洋的雲層
themselves on the north eastern slopes. With an annual precipitation of 2700 mm per year,
在東北坡上消散。該地區 年降水量達 2,700 毫米，
it is one of the most precipitous regions of Central America, and despite the thin soil,
是中美洲降水量最大的地區之一。 儘管土壤貧瘠，但
a prosperous tropical rainforest has developed on the slopes of these mountains.
這些山脈的山坡上仍然生長著茂盛的熱帶雨林。
Pico Cristal, the highest point of the mountain range,
克里斯特爾峰是 該山脈的最高點，海拔
rises to an elevation of 1,300 meters above the sea level but it pales in comparison to
1300 米， 但與南部的鄰近山峰相比，它就顯得黯然失色了
its southern neighbor. Stretching along Cuba's southeastern coastline for 140 kilometers,
。沿著古巴 東南海岸線綿延 140 公里的
the Sierra Maestra mountains boast Pico Turquino, which with 1970 meters is
馬埃斯特拉山脈擁有 圖爾基諾峰，海拔 1970 米，是
the island's tallest peak and one of the highest summits in the Greater Antilles.
島上的最高峰，也是 大安的列斯群島最高的山峰之一。這座山峰
Standing as a rainforest covered tower over the Caribbean Sea,
聳立在 加勒比海上，宛如一座被熱帶雨林覆蓋的塔樓。
this summit is actually the only place in Cuba where snowfall has been recorded,
事實上，它是 古巴唯一有降雪記錄的地方，
with the winter of 1900 bringing this peculiarity into the tropics.
1900 年的冬天， 熱帶地區出現了這種奇特的現象。自 17 世紀中葉以來，
The area in and around Pico Turquino has been a hotspot for coffee cultivation since the mid 17th
皮科圖爾基諾山及其周邊地區一直是 咖啡種植的熱點地區
century, and this practice, which has been started by Spanish and French Colonialists,
，這種 由西班牙和法國殖民者開始的種植方式
has continued to this date, with 92% of Cuba’s coffee coming from the Sierra Maestra Mountains.
一直延續至今，古巴 92% 的 咖啡產自馬埃斯特拉山脈。
Each of the Cuban mountain ranges has one particular crop which grows exceptionally
古巴的每個山脈都有一種 特別適合生長的作物
well there. The central Escambray Mountains for example, have been dominated by the cultivation
。例如，埃斯坎布雷山脈中部地區 一直以甘蔗種植為主
of sugarcane, with the mountain's southern slope having been the heart of the global
，山脈的 南坡一直是全球
sugar industry. Since this industry however was built through the blood of 30.000 slaves,
製糖業的中心。然而，由於這個行業是用 3 萬名奴隸的鮮血建立起來的，
not much of this industry is left today, and a large UNESCO heritage site covering
如今這個行業所剩無幾，而 覆蓋著
the terraced fields and old sugar mills, reminds us of this dark part of history.
梯田和舊糖廠的大型聯合國教科文組織世界遺產地， 提醒著我們這段黑暗的歷史。
Far on the western side of Cuba, the traditional industry has persisted though, with many
在古巴西部的遙遠地區，傳統 產業依然存在，許多
international connoisseurs worshipping what mother nature is giving us here. Just the right levels of
國際鑑賞家對 大自然賜予這裡的禮物讚不絕口。適宜的
precipitation, sunlight and temperature, together with a soil that is rich in nitrates, calcium and
降水量、陽光和溫度，加上 富含硝酸鹽、鈣和錳的土壤，使得這裡的菸草葉子
manganese, result in the leaves of the tobacco plant here being hailed as the best in the world.
被譽為世界上最好的。在
Between these far apart mountain ranges, flat valleys are home to the rest of the
這些相距遙遠的山脈之間， 平坦的山谷是古巴其他農業區的所在地。
Cuban agriculture, but despite this heavy human impact on the landscape, several unique regions
儘管人類活動 對這片土地造成了巨大的影響，但仍然保留著幾個獨特的區域，這些區域
still persists, which couldn't be more different from each other, bringing us to
彼此之間截然不同。這就引出了
Chapter 2: The Ecoregions According to the Köppen climate
第二章：生態區。 根據柯本氣候分類法（
classification, which is a system commonly used to subdivide the world into different climatic
一種常用的將 世界劃分為不同氣候
zones and subzones, nearly the entirety of Cuba is considered tropical Savannah,
帶和亞帶的系統）， 古巴幾乎全部被認為是熱帶稀樹草原，
with only the north eastern and western coastal zones behind the mountains being
只有山脈後面的東北部和西部 沿海地區被
classified as tropical rainforest. This however has not held back
歸類為熱帶雨林。但這並沒有 阻止
the ecoregions from developing and sprawling in many different varieties.
生態區域以 多種不同形式發展和擴張。
The four mountain ranges that we have discussed already are largely covered with cuban moist,
我們已經討論過的四個山脈大部分被古巴濕潤、
dry and pine forest ecoregions, which all have their unique characteristics based on
乾燥和松林生態區覆蓋，這些生態區都 具有其獨特的特徵，這些特徵取決於土壤的
the fertility and moisture retention ability of the soil, whether they have a distinctive dry
肥力和保水能力， 是否有明顯的旱季
and wet seasons, and by the dominant tree type like broadleaf, or deciduous trees.
和雨季，以及主要的樹種 類型，如闊葉樹或落葉樹。
Moving closer to the coast, the more peculiar ecoregions start to emerge,
越靠近海岸，越是 奇特的生態區域開始顯現，
with the southern coastline under the Nipe Sagua Baracoa Mountains coming straight out of an
尼佩薩瓜巴拉科阿山脈下的南部海岸線彷彿來自
alien planet. Since the rain shadow effect creates extreme aridity, the precipitation
外星。由於雨影效應 造成了極度乾旱，
rate here is the lowest anywhere in Cuba, which has created the so-called Cuban Cactus Shrub.
這裡的降水量是古巴所有地方中最低的，這就 形成了所謂的古巴仙人掌灌木叢。
Succulent plants, meaning plants with the ability to store large amounts of water,
多肉植物，也就是 能儲存大量水分的植物，正在骨骼狀的
are populating the skeletal limestone soil and despite the less than 800mm
石灰岩土壤中繁衍生息。 儘管年降水量不足 800 毫米，
of annual precipitation, with dry periods ranging between 9 and 11 months per year,
且每年乾旱期 長達 9 至 11 個月，但
they have formed the basis of an extraordinary ecosystem.
它們仍然構成了 非凡生態系統的基礎。
The Cuban Rock Iguana, the Pigmy Eleuth and flower bats have adjusted to this harsh environment,
古巴岩鬣蜥、侏儒蝙蝠和花蝠 已經適應了這種惡劣的環境，
but economic incentives are putting this environment at risk, slowly replacing the endemic
但經濟利益正在 危及這種環境，當地特有的帶刺灌木正逐漸被
thorny bushes with Sisal, a plant cultivated for its stiff fibres used in rope manufacturing.
劍麻所取代，劍麻是一種 因其堅硬的纖維而種植的植物，該纖維用於繩索製造。沿著
Further down the coast to the west, the moisture suddenly becomes abundant, creating
海岸線向西繼續前行， 水分突然變得充沛，形成了與
the biological opposite of the cactus shrublands. Starting from the shoreline of the Bay of Pigs,
仙人掌灌木叢截然相反的生物環境。 從上世紀也曾載入史冊的豬灣海岸線開始
which also had its entry in the history books in the last century, the vast Zapata swamp stretches
，廣大的薩帕塔沼澤綿延
for over 100 kilometers and is the largest representative of the Cuban Wetland Ecoregion.
100 多公里，是古巴 濕地生態區最大的代表。
Spanning 4% of Cuba’s territory, this vast swamp features caves, sinkholes,
這片廣闊的沼澤佔古巴領土的 4%， 擁有洞穴、落水洞、窪地
depressions, and floodplains that form a dynamic hydrographic network of marshes,
和洪氾區，形成了一個 動態的水文網絡，包括沼澤、
freshwater lagoons, and transition zones leading to the Caribbean Sea. Daily tidal
淡水潟湖和過渡帶，最終匯入 加勒比海。每日潮汐
movements breathe life into this ecosystem by pushing water masses through the swamp,
運動 推動水團流經沼澤，為這片生態系統注入了生機；
and seasonal floods regularly cover the savannah of the hinterland prompting the
季節性洪水定期淹沒 內陸的稀樹草原，促使
migration of hundreds of thousands birds to depart from these wetlands.
成千上萬隻 鳥類離開這些濕地遷徙。
Within the swamps marine ecosystem, sharks, crocodiles and manatees are feeding on the
在沼澤海洋生態系統中，鯊魚、 鱷魚和海牛以
abundance of fish and vegetation, and the most peculiar of birds is soaring through
豐富的魚類和植物為食，而 最奇特的鳥類則在
the dense flora. At 1.6 grams and with wing flaps of up to 80 times per second,
茂密的植物群中翱翔。蜂鳥體重僅1.6克， 翅膀每秒可扇動80次，它們在
the bee hummingbird is rushing from flower to flower, and keeping the whole ecosystem running.
花叢間穿梭， 維持整個生態系的運作。
Much of the remaining coastline of Cuba is covered by the 6th and final ecoregion,
古巴剩餘的大部分海岸線被 第六個也是最後一個生態區——紅
called the mangrove. Mangroves cover 5.1% of Cuba’s land area—accounting for 20% of its
樹林覆蓋。紅樹林覆蓋了古巴5.1%的 土地面積，佔其
remaining forest and protecting over half its coastline from natural disasters. Particularly
剩餘森林的20%，並保護了其一半以上的 海岸線免受自然災害的侵襲。尤其是
the southern coast is prone to hurricanes and storm surges, which are being slowed down by
南部沿海地區容易遭受颶風和風暴潮的侵襲，而
the kilometer deep network of Mangrove roots, which hold everything in place.
深達數公里的紅樹林 根系網絡減緩了颶風和風暴潮的來襲速度，並將一切固定到位。
While being an important part of the islands sea defence turing times of distress from
雖然它是島嶼海防的重要組成部分，能夠抵禦
mother nature, it also plays a vital role in balancing the mass balance of the ecoregion,
大自然的侵襲，但它在平衡 生態區的物質平衡方面也發揮著至關重要的作用，
since sediments from the receding tidal swells are being trapped in the root network, slowing
因為退潮時的沉積物 被困在根系中，
down coastal erosion and readjusting the sea bed level in light of the global sea level rise.
減緩了海岸侵蝕，並 在全球海平面上升的情況下重新調整了海底水平。
As a harbour of life for all sorts of species, the mangroves are the
紅樹林是各種物種的生命港灣，
most protected habitat of Cuba, and not just cover large swaths of the main island's coast,
也是古巴受保護程度最高的棲息地，不僅 覆蓋了主島海岸的大片區域，
but also many of the surrounding keys and islets. While the country of Cuba is often
還覆蓋了許多周圍的島嶼和 小島。雖然人們通常
only associated with its main island, there are actually thousands of these smaller islands,
只將古巴與其主島聯繫起來，但 實際上古巴有數千個較小的島嶼，
making Cuba a massive archipelago in itself and bringing us to the third and final chapter
使古巴本身成為一個巨大的群島，這也 引出了我們的第三章，也是最後一章。
Chapter 3: The greater Archipelago Across its entire territory,
第三章：更大的群島。古巴 在其整個領土上由
the country of Cuba consists of a staggering 4195 islands, which are grouped into 4
驚人的 4195 個島嶼組成，這些島嶼在
archipelagos off the northern and southern coastline in the shallow nearshore areas.
北部和南部 海岸線附近的淺水近岸區域被分為 4 個群島。
The archipelago with the most islands is located along the central northern coast and accounts for
島嶼最多的群島位於 中北部沿海地區，在
2500 islands along its 450 kilometer extent. Many of the larger islands here are connected through
其 450 公里的範圍內共有 2500 個島嶼。 這裡許多較大的島嶼透過公路網連接起來，這些公路網由
a road network consisting of long causeways which were constructed at the end of the last century,
上世紀末修建的長堤組成，
now allowing for the development of luxury beach resorts on the white sandy beaches.
現在使得 在白色沙灘上開發豪華海灘度假村成為可能。然而，群島的
The eastern and western extends of this archipelago however are virtually untouched,
東部和西部 幾乎未受破壞，
harbouring much of the Cuban mangrove forests and wetlands. These islands are much younger
保留了古巴的大部分紅樹林 和濕地。這些島嶼
than the main island and often just consist of a large pile of sand which sticks out of the sea.
比主島年輕得多，通常只是從 海中伸出的一大堆沙子。
Their existence today is thanks to thousands of former coral reefs, which teemed the seabed
它們今天的存在要歸功於
around 130.000 years ago, during a time when the sea level was much higher than today. Upon their
大約 13 萬年前遍布海底的數千個珊瑚礁，當時 海平面比現在高得多。珊瑚
death, the coral skeleton trapped free flowing sediments from the ocean currents, which have then
死後，其骨骼捕獲了來自洋流的自由流動沉積物，而自那時以來，地球經歷了
been exposed by the roughly 25m of sea level drop that earth has experienced since then.
大約 25 公尺的海平面下降，這些沉積物才得以暴露出來。
Today, these keys are threatened by the very mechanic that created them,
如今，這些鑰匙正受到 創造它們的機械本身的威脅：
with significant erosion from wind and water removing the sand, and the
風 和水的嚴重侵蝕帶走了沙子，而不斷
rising sea level threatening to drown them again. Luckily, the mangroves are slowing
上升的海平面又威脅著要再次淹沒它們 。幸運的是，紅樹林減緩了
these developments but it is uncertain exactly how long they will remain to be appreciated.
這些發展趨勢，但 它們究竟能保留多久供人欣賞，目前還不得而知。
On the other side of the Cuban main island lie the Queen's Gardens,
在古巴主島的另一側是 皇后花園，這是
named by Christopher Columbus in honor of Spain’s queen upon his sighting. Known as the "Galapagos
克里斯多福·哥倫佈在發現它時，為了紀念西班牙 女王而命名的。
of the Caribbean," this archipelago boasts some of Cuba’s most pristine underwater landscapes,
這個群島被稱為“加勒比​​海的加拉巴哥群島”，擁有 古巴一些最原始的水下景觀，充滿
with vibrant coral reefs teeming with groupers, reef sharks, and American crocodiles that attract
活力的珊瑚礁中棲息著石斑魚、 礁鯊和美洲鱷，吸引著
divers and snorkelers from all over the world. Designated as a nature reserve,
來自世界各地的潛水員和浮潛者 。這些島嶼被指定為自然保護區，
these islands have no permanent inhabitants, and strict regulations on tourism and fishing
沒有常住居民， 嚴格的旅遊和捕魚法規
ensure their preservation. In recent decades, fishing has actually been banned outright
確保了它們的保護。近幾十年來，公園邊界內 實際上已經完全禁止捕魚
within the parks boundaries, which has since then turned the marine ecosystem into a fish
，這使得 海洋生態系統變成了魚類
spawning machine, benefitting not just the biodiversity, but also the fishing industry.
產卵機器，不僅有利於 生物多樣性，也有利於漁業。
The catch in the deeper waters has increased dramatically since the
自從
adaptation of this policy, leading to fisherman and conservationists
這項政策實施以來，深水區的漁獲量大幅增加，導致 漁民和環保人士
now pulling on the same rope, to preserve this wilderness.
現在齊心協力，共同 保護這片荒野。在
180 kilometers west of these underwater worlds, the Canarreos Archipelago starts stretching for
這些水下世界以西 180 公里處， 卡納雷奧斯群島開始
300 kilometers around the Zapata Swamp, and among the 350 islands of this archipelago, Cuba's second
向薩帕塔沼澤延伸 300 公里。在 這個群島的 350 個島嶼中，古巴第二
largest island lies right in the middle of it The Isle of Youth as it was named by Fidel Castro,
大島就位於其中心。 這座被菲德爾·卡斯特羅命名為“青春島”的島嶼，
was formerly known as the Isle of Pines, which today best describes its vegetation. The low
以前被稱為“松樹島”， 如今這個名字最能貼切地形容島上的植被。
lying ridges of the north are nearly completely covered in Caribbean pine, while the southern
北部的低窪山脊幾乎完全 被加勒比松樹覆蓋，而南部
plains are covered in a massive swamp, similar to the Zapata Swamp of the main island, housing
平原則被一片巨大的沼澤覆蓋， 類似於主島的薩帕塔沼澤，擁有
an incredible hydrological network and giving a home to hundreds of thousands of migratory birds.
令人難以置信的水文網絡，並為數 十萬隻候鳥提供了棲息地。
All in all, Cuba has an astounding geographical diversity along its thin latitudinal extent,
總而言之，古巴 在其狹長的緯度範圍內擁有驚人的地理多樣性，
covering misty mountains, idyllic beaches, fertile plains and slopes,
涵蓋了雲霧繚繞的山脈、田園詩般的 海灘、肥沃的平原和山坡，
and some of the most interesting and best preserved wetlands in the world.
以及世界上一些最有趣、 保存最完好的濕地。
I hope you have learned something new on this journey across the island of Cuba. If you want to
我希望你在這次 古巴島之旅中學到了一些新知識。如果你想在下一部
get notified when the next mini-documentary comes out, you can subscribe. And if you want to support
迷你紀錄片發佈時收到通知 ，可以訂閱。如果您想
the channel even more, you can now also leave a small donation at my Buy Me a Coffee Page with
進一步支持本頻道，現在還可以透過螢幕中間或描述中的鏈接，在 我的“請我喝咖啡”頁面上留下小額捐贈
the link in the middle of the screen or in the description. See you in the next video, cheers.
。下個影片見，謝謝。